<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Tiruvaṇṇāmalai, Aruṇācaleśvara, time of Kṛṣṇadevarāya, Śaka year 1438</title>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                <persName ref="part:reda">
                    <forename>Renato</forename>
                    <surname>Dávalos</surname>
                </persName>
                <persName ref="part:emfr">
                    <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                    <surname>Francis</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>DHARMA</authority>
            <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
            <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSTamilNadu00023</idno>
            <availability>
                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                    <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported
                        Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit
                        https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to
                        Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View,
                        California, 94041, USA.</p>
                    <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                </licence>
            </availability>
            <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                    <idno/>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <summary>Records various donations of Kṛṣṇadevarāya at the temple of Tiruvaṇṇāmalai: garments and jewelry; various buildings; food offerings and temple services; appointment, among others, of sixty dancing girls, ten reciters (<foreign>otuvār</foreign>) of sacred hymns (<foreign>tiruppāṭṭu</foreign>), two brahmins performing <foreign>adhyayana</foreign>.</summary>
                    <!--METADATA Second prākāra, north wall (outside), above. Incomplete? 1517 CE -->
                </msContents>
                <physDesc>
                    <handDesc>
                        <p/>
                        <p/>
                    </handDesc>
                </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>The project DHARMA has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC)
                under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant
                agreement no 809994).</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <schemaRef type="guide" key="EGDv01"
            url="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02888186"/>
        <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="bib" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9\-\_]+)"
                replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/1633743/erc-dharma/items/tag/$1">
                <p>Public URIs with the prefix bib to point to a Zotero Group Library named
                    ERC-DHARMA whose data are open to the public.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="part" matchPattern="([a-z]+)"
                replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml#$1">
                <p>Internal URIs using the part prefix to point to person elements in the
                    <ref>DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml</ref> file.</p>
            </prefixDef>
        </listPrefixDef>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change who="part:reda" when="2024-04-18" status="draft">Creation of the file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text xml:space="preserve">
<body>
	<!--@Renato: check again Grantha from estampages-->	
<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:83215">
	
    <ab xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:grantha maturity:83215">
        <lb n="1"/><g type="pc"/> <hi rend="grantha">śubham as<unclear>tu</unclear> svasti</hi>
    </ab>
    
    <p>
        <hi rend="grantha">śrīma</hi>ṉ-<hi rend="grantha">mahā</hi>-Irācātirāca-Irāca-<hi rend="grantha">pa</hi>rame<hi rend="grantha">śva</hi>ra<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied> mū-v-arāyar kaṇṭaṉ Ariya-Irāya-vipāṭa<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied> Aṭṭa-tikku-Irāya-maṉō<hi rend="grantha">bha</hi>yaṅkara<hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied> pāṣai</hi>kku-t tappu-v-arāyar kaṇṭa<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied> <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>pūrvva</unclear></hi>-<hi rend="grantha">da<choice><sic>kṣṇa</sic><corr>kṣiṇa</corr></choice></hi>-pacci<hi rend="grantha">ma-samu</hi>ttirāccura<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied> yava-rācciya-<hi rend="grantha">st</hi>tā<hi rend="grantha">bha</hi>ṉācāriya<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied> <hi rend="grantha">gaja</hi>pati-vi<hi rend="grantha">bhā</hi>ṭa<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied> <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>-vīra-p-<hi rend="grantha">pra</hi><unclear>tā</unclear>pa-<hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>-vīra-kiru<hi rend="grantha">ṣṇa</hi>-tēva-<hi rend="grantha">mahā</hi>rāyar vicaiya-nakarattilē Iruntu
        <hi rend="grantha">pūrvva</hi>-tikku vicai<supplied reason="omitted">ya</supplied>-yāttirai Āka Eḻunt-aruḷi Utaiyakiri-turkkam mutalē kai-k-koṇṭu Irāvutta-rāya-<hi rend="grantha">mahā</hi>-pāttiṟattaiyum piṭittu-k-koṇṭu Attaṅki viṉikoṇṭai vellaṅ-koṇṭai nākāccuṉi-koṇṭai taṅ<unclear>koṭu</unclear> 
        <lb n="2"/>ketavāram Itu mutal-āṉa kiri-turkkaṅkaḷ <hi rend="grantha">st</hi>tala-turkkaṅkaḷ <hi rend="grantha">Eka</hi>tāṭi Āka kai-k-koṇṭu koṇṭavīṭṭu-turkattil mēlē viṭṭu Ālakkai piṭittu Anta-t turkattaiyum kai-k-koṇṭu <hi rend="grantha">pra</hi>tā<hi rend="grantha" >pa</hi>-ruttira-kēca-pati-rāyar kumārar vīra-p-pattiṟa-rāyaṉaiyum kumāra-Ampīra-pāttiṟaṉ kumāraṉ nāra<unclear>nari</unclear>tēvu Irāccūra malluvakāṉṉaṉ Uttaṇṭa-kāṉaṉ śaṉṉiyāla-kacavā-pāttiṟaṉ <unclear>pū</unclear>cappāṭi Irācci Irācaṉ <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>-nātarācaṉ Ila<hi rend="grantha">kṣimi</hi>-<choice><sic>m</sic><corr>p</corr></choice>ati Irācaṉ paccima-vāla-cantira-<hi rend="grantha">mahā-pā</hi>ttiraṉ Ivarkaḷ mutal-āṉa pāttirar cāvanta<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied> Āṉa maṉṉiyar
        <lb n="3"/>kaḷaiyum cīvakkiṟākam āka piṭittu-k-koṇṭu Avarkaḷukku Apaiyatāṉam koṭuttu taraṇi-k-koṭṭai Amarēcurattil tulā-puru<hi rend="grantha">ṣa-mahā</hi>tāṉam paṇṇi tirumpi vicaiya-nakarattukku Eḻunt-aruḷi-c c<supplied reason="omitted">ā</supplied><hi rend="grantha">mpr<unclear>ā</unclear>jji</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">m·</hi> paṇṇi-k-koṇṭu piṉṉaiyum kaliṅka-tēcam tikku-vicaiyam Āka <choice><sic>te</sic><corr><hi rend="grantha">be</hi></corr></choice>cavāṭaikku Eḻunt-aruḷi koṇṭa-p-paḷḷi-t tuṟkamum kai-k-koṇṭu Anta tuṟkattiṉ mēlē Irunta <hi rend="grantha">prakarāśa</hi>ṉ cira-c-cantira-ma<hi rend="grantha">hā</hi>-pāttiraṉ pōṭṭu<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉa-<hi rend="grantha">mah<supplied reason="omitted">ā</supplied></hi>-pāttiraṉ vicili-kāṉāṉ Ivarkaḷ mutal Āṉavarkaḷaiyum cīvakiṟakam Āka piṭittu apaiya-t-tāṉamum
        <lb n="4"/>koṭuttu Anta-kiri Uṇṭān-koṇṭa Uṟuḷa-koṇṭa Aruva-p-paḷḷi calli-p-paḷḷi kanti-ko<supplied reason="omitted">ṇ</supplied>ṭai kappaluvāyu-koṇṭai kampam Eṭṭu kaṉaka-kiri caṅkara-kiri Itu mutal Āṉa teluṅkaraṇaiya-t tuṟkam Ekatāṭi Āka kai-k-koṇṭu ciṅkāttiri poṭṭunūṟku Eḻunt-aruḷi Aṅkē ceya-t-tampam nāṭṭi makā-tānam ceytu tirumpi 
        Irāca-mayēntira-varattukku Eḻunt-aruḷi tammuṭa tēviyār ciṉṉātevi-Ammaṉ tiru-malai-tēvi-Amman Ivarkaḷ kaiyilē makā-tāṉam paṇṇivittu vica<supplied reason="omitted">iya</supplied>ṉakarattukku Eḻunt-aruḷi
    </p>
    <ab xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:grantha maturity:83215">		
        <hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi>
    </ab>
    <p>
        ceyā<surplus>p</surplus><hi rend="grantha">bh<unclear>y</unclear>u</hi>taiya-cālivā<hi rend="grantha">ka</hi>ṉa-<hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>ka-varu<hi rend="grantha">ṣa</hi>m 
        <lb n="5"/><num value="1438"><g type="numeral">1000</g> 4 <g type="numeral">100</g> 3 <g type="numeral">10</g> 8</num>-ṉ mēl cellā niṉṟa tātu-<hi rend="grantha">sam</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">t·sa</hi>rattu makara-nāyaṟṟu pūṟuva-pa<hi rend="grantha">kṣa</hi>ttu tiṟaiyotēciyum cōma-vārattil nāḷ tiru-v-aṇṇāmalaikku Eḻunt-aruḷi Uṭaiyār tiru-v-aṇṇāmalai Uṭaiya nayiṉāraiyum nācciyār Uṇṇāmulai-Ammaiy<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>u</corr></choice>m teṇṭan paṇṇi Uṭaiyavaṟku māṇikka-patakkam Oṉṟu nākāparaṇam Oṉṟu poṉṉā mālai vākupuri Uttar<choice><orig><unclear>i</unclear></orig><reg>ī</reg></choice>yam piṟavāḷai Intira-vimāṉam poṉṉa-k keṇṭikai veḷḷi-vintikai tiru-mañcaṉam Eṭukka veḷḷi-k-kuṭam It-taṉaiyum camaittu tiri-cūlattukku poṉṉum pūci pati<choice><orig>n</orig><reg>ṉ</reg></choice> oru nilai-kōpuram Āyira-k-kāl-maṇṭapam Itukku muṉ vacantaṉ teṟ<unclear>pai-t tiru</unclear>nālukku ceyvitta tirukkuḷamum Itu
        <lb n="6" break="no"/>kku taṇṇīr vara takkatāka veṭṭiṉa tirumalai-tēvi-Ammaṉ camuttiram Eḻām tiru-nāḷ maṇṭapam makara-caṅkiṟānti-maṇṭapam viṉāyakan tēr tiru-vīti It-taṉaiyum kaṭṭivittu vāṇavataraiyaṉ kōpura-vācal katavu kāl paṭi Uttama-Ōḻaṉ tiru-vācal katavu kāl mēl-paṭi mēl-palakaṇi Uṇṇāmulai-nācciyār kōyil caṭṭai-p-peru perumāḷ kōyilukku mēṟku vācal katavu katavu kāl veṅkala-p-paṭi vācal katavu katavu kāl tūpi It-taṉaiyum poṉ-pūci keṟpakiṟaka-vācal muṉ-muka-pattiṟam kuṟaṭu kaṭṭi mēl kampam niṟuti koṭunkai Iṭṭu mēl poṉpūcivittu maṭa-p-paḷimuṉ veṭṭivitta Ārā-Amuta kiṇaṟu 
    </p>
    <p>
        <gap quantity="4" unit="character" reason="undefined"/> yavaṟku pañcāmiṟutam Apicēkam nāḷ
        <lb n="7"/>Oṉṟukku Aruci Aṟukalam nēy paṭi muṉṟu vella<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied> palam Oṉpatum payaṟu pa<unclear>la</unclear>m nālu Uppu paṭi Oṉṟu miḷaku paṭi kāl cantaṉam kaḻañcu mu-p-pattu Oṉṟu karpūram kaḻañc' arai taṭṭu puḻuku kaḻañcu Arai Inta cantikku viṭṭa tēvaṭiyār pēr Aṟu-patu Atukku takka meḷam tiru-mañcaṉam Eṭuppār pēr pattu tiru-p-pāṭṭu Otuvār pēr pattu Attiya<choice><orig>n</orig><reg>ṉ</reg></choice>a-pirāmaṇar Iraṇṭu pallakku cervaikku Attiya<choice><orig>n</orig><reg>ṉ</reg></choice>am Ōtum pēr Iraṇṭu
    </p>
    
</div>
	
<div type="apparatus">
	
    <listApp>
        
        <!--<app loc="0">
            <lem>...</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Srinivasan+Reiniche1990_01">...</rdg>
            </app>-->
        
        <app loc="1">
            <lem><hi rend="grantha"><unclear>pūrvva</unclear></hi>-<hi rend="grantha">da<choice><sic>kṣṇa</sic><corr>kṣiṇa</corr></choice></hi>°</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Srinivasan+Reiniche1990_01"><hi rend="grantha">dakṣṇa</hi>°</rdg>
            </app>        
        
        <app loc="2">
            <lem>nāra<unclear>nari</unclear>tēvu</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Srinivasan+Reiniche1990_01">nāraṉ<hi rend="grantha">har</hi>itevu</rdg>
        </app>
        
        <app loc="3">
            <lem>pōṭṭu<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉa°</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Srinivasan+Reiniche1990_01">poṭa<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉa°</rdg>
        </app>
        
        <app loc="4">
            <lem>°<hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>ka°</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Srinivasan+Reiniche1990_01">°<hi rend="grantha">śa</hi>ka°</rdg>
        </app>
        
        <app loc="5">
            <lem>Ammaiy<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>u</corr></choice>m</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Srinivasan+Reiniche1990_01">Ammaiy<choice><sic>ai</sic><corr>u</corr></choice>m</rdg>
        </app>
        
    </listApp>
    
</div>
      	
<div type="translation" source="bib:Srinivasan+Reiniche1990_01">
	
	<p n="1-4">Let there be auspiciousness! Hail! Śrī-Vīrapratāpa-śrī-Vīra-Kiruṣṇatēvamahārāyar, who was an illustrious <foreign>mahā-irācātirāca</foreign>, <foreign>irācaparameśvara</foreign>, the enemy of the three kings, who destroyed the enemy kings, who caused fear in the minds of the kings of the eight directions, who punished the kings who disobeyed his orders, who was the ruler over the oceans in the east, the south and the west, who was the preceptor for establishing the kingdom of Yava and the vanquisher of Gajapati, started from Vicaiyanakara on his conquest of the regions in the east. First, he conquered the fort of Utaiyakiri, and then he captured Irāvuttarāyamahāpāttira. Afterwards he captured, at one bound, the hill forts and land forts like those of Attaṅki, Viṉikoṇṭai, Vellaṅkoṇṭai, Nākāccuṉikoṇṭai, Teṅ<unclear>koṭu</unclear>, Kētavāram, and other forts. Then he took the fort atop the hill at Koṇṭa-vīṭu and captured the hill also. Then he captured alive Vīrappattirarāyaṉ, the son of Prātāparuttira Kecapatirāyar, Nāruṉi<unclear>hari</unclear>tēvu, the son of Kumāra-Ampīra-pāttiṟaṉ, Malluva-kāṉaṉ of Rāccūr <supplied reason="explanation">Raichur</supplied>, Uttaṇṭa-kāṉaṉ, Canniyāl Kacavā-pāttiraṉ, Śrīnāta-rācaṉ, the king of the Pūccappāṭi kingdom, Ilakṣmipati Irācaṉ, Paccima-Vālacantira-mahāpāttiraṉ and other <foreign>cāmantas</foreign> of this category. He gave them protection from fear. Then he performed the <foreign>tulāpuruṣa-mahātāṉa</foreign> in the temple of Amarēcura at Taraṇikkoṭṭai. He then came back to Vicaiyanakara and ruled.
	    Again he started on the conquest of the Kaliṅga country. On the way he arrived at De(Be?)cavāṭai. Then he took the fort at Koṇṭapaḷḷi and captured alive Prakarācaṉ-Ciraccantira-mahāpāttiraṉ who was in that fort, Pōṭajaṉa-mahāpāttiraṉ, Vicilikkāṉaṉ and others. He gave them protection from fear. Then he captured at one bound the forts at Antakiri, Uṇṭākoṇṭa, Uṟuḷakoṇṭa, Aruvappaḷḷi, Callippaḷḷi, Kantikoṇṭai, Kappalavāyu-koṇṭai, Kampameṭṭu, Kanakakiri, Caṅkarakiri and others of the Teluṅkaraṇaiya. Then he arrived at Ciṅkāttiri Poṭṭunūṟu where he erected a victory pillar and performed the <foreign>makātāṉa</foreign> <supplied reason="explanation">great gift</supplied>.
	    Then he returned to Irācamayēntiravaram where he caused his queens Ciṉṉātēvi-ammaṉ and Tirumalaitēvi-amman to make the <foreign>makā-tāṉa</foreign>. Afterwards he came back to Vicaiyanakaram.</p>
<p n="4-6">Then on Monday the 13th day in the bright fortnight of the month of Makara of the year Tātu in the expired; victorious and wonderful Cālivāhaṉa Śaka year 1438<note>January 5, 1517.</note>, he went to Tiruvaṇṇāmalai where he worshipped the god Tiruvaṇṇāmalai-uṭaiya Nayiṉār and the goddess Uṇṇāmulai nācciyār. Then he caused the following to be made to the god: a necklace made of emerald, a <foreign>nākāparaṇa</foreign>, a garland made of gold, a <foreign>vākapuri</foreign>, an upper cloth, an <foreign>intira-vimānam</foreign> made of coral, a golden <foreign>keṇṭikai</foreign>, a silver <foreign>vintikai</foreign>, and one silver pot for carrying water for bathing. Then he caused the gilding of the trident, the building of the 11-storeyed <foreign>kōpura</foreign> and the 1000-pillared <foreign>maṇṭapa</foreign>, a tank for the floating festival during the period of Vasanta (i.e., summer), in front of the above <foreign>maṇṭapa</foreign>, the digging up of a tank called Tirumalaitēvi-ammaṉ Camuttiram for supplying water to the above tank, the building of the <foreign>maṇṭapa</foreign> for the seventh-day festival, and of the <foreign>maṇṭapa</foreign> for conducting the festival of Makara-caṅkirānti, and the making of a car for Vināyaka land constructing a street. Then he caused the gilding of the door, doorway and the sill of the <foreign>kōpura</foreign> entrance of the enclosure called the Vāṇavataraiyaṉ-tiruvācal; the door, door-jamb, upper sill, upper window of the Uttamacōḻaṉ-tiruvācal; and also door, door-jamb, of the west gate of the Caṭṭaperuperumāḷkōyil in the temple of Uṇṇāmulainācciyār and gilding its sill made of bronze, door, door-jamb and a <foreign>tūpi</foreign>. Then he built the platform in front of the entryway of the <foreign>sanctum sanctorum</foreign>. On it he erected a pillar with cornice which was gilded. Then he dug up a well called Ārā-amuta in front of the kitchen.
</p>
	<p n="6-7">Then he endowed for the purpose of food offering and other services on the occasion of bathing the deity daily with <foreign>pañcāmirutam</foreign> <supplied reason="explanation">a mixture containing five articles</supplied>, six <foreign>kalam</foreign> of rice, three measures of ghee, nine <foreign>palam</foreign> of jaggery, four <foreign>palam</foreign> of green gram, one measure of salt, quarter measure of pepper, 31 <foreign>kalañcu</foreign> of sandal paste, 1 1/2 <foreign>kaḻañcu</foreign> of civet. To attend at the time of this service sixty dancing girls were engaged together with the necessary <foreign>mēḷam</foreign> <supplied reason="explanation">appurtenances</supplied>, ten persons for the purpose of carrying water for the bathing of the deity, ten persons for the recitation of the <foreign>tiruppāṭṭu</foreign> <supplied reason="explanation">i.e., the <foreign>Dēvāram</foreign> hymns</supplied>, two brahmins for the <foreign>adhyayana</foreign> <supplied reason="explanation">i.e., reciting the <foreign>Vēdas</foreign></supplied> and two persons for the <foreign>adhyayana</foreign> at the time of the procession of the deity in the palanquin ...</p>
      		
</div>
      	
<!--<div type="commentary">
	
</div>-->
      	
<div type="bibliography">
    
    <p>Edited and translated in <bibl><ptr target="bib:Srinivasan+Reiniche1990_01"/></bibl> (TVM 389).</p>
    <p>This revised edition by Renato Dávalos and Emmanuel Francis based on EFEO estampages (EO 247-278).</p>      
    <listBibl type="primary">
        
        <bibl n="TV">
            <ptr target="bib:Srinivasan+Reiniche1990_01"/>
            <citedRange unit="page">482-485</citedRange>
            <citedRange unit="item">389</citedRange>
        </bibl>              
        
    </listBibl>
    
</div>

      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

